So today's דף daf is ד. daled. Today's דף daf is ד.
daled. We pick up at the bottom of ג עמוד ב Gimmel
Amud Beis and the discussion is the position of the statement of
רבי חייא Rebbi Chiya that the same way somebody who is a
מודה במקצת modeh b'miktzas admits to part of a claim is made,
he owes a hundred, he admits to part of it, he has
to take a שבועה, shvua, the same would be true if he
had denied it all and witnesses say that he was liable in
part even though as the גמרא Gemara concedes the whole argument that
he is sort of rationalizing and so on and that a שבועה
shvua will be effective
is less present in the case of witnesses.
Nevertheless, you know, the witnesses do establish some substantiate to some degree
the legitimacy of the claim and even though the rationalization might be
less, nevertheless you make a שבועה. shvua. And that's based on a
formal argument that the power of witnesses is greater than the power
of one's own admission. So even though the logic of this case
itself, the admission might be more of a basis for a שבועה,
shvua, but in terms of a sort of formal קל וחומר, kal
vachomer, the weight of witnesses is greater. How does the גמרא Gemara
establish the weight of witnesses is greater? Because it says witnesses can
make somebody pay a קנס knas and somebody's own admission, you know,
cannot make them pay a קנס. knas. Okay. So where were we?
Okay. But the גמרא Gemara says but one minute, you know, your
own admission is weightier than witnesses because your own admission makes you
bring a קרבן korban and because part of bringing a קרבן, korban,
coming up to ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, is your acceptance of guilt,
whereas witnesses don't make you bring a קרבן. korban. And the גמרא
Gemara says no, this could be רבי מאיר. Rebbi Meir. רבי מאיר
Rebbi Meir also says witnesses are stronger than admission as a sort
of a cross-the-board type of a thing and he would say that
witnesses would also make you bring a קרבן korban even if you
deny you've done it. Witnesses say you do it, you bring a
קרבן. korban. Okay. So therefore we're still trying to argue that across
the board witnesses are stronger than your own admission. So yeah.
How does the concept of אין אדם משים עצמו רשע ein adam
meisim atzmo rasha consist with that?
In other words— Well,
that's exactly why your admission cannot make you get קנס knas or
get a lashes or anything of that nature because you're— so what
do you have— but your admission can make you pay money. Money
is not being a רשע. rasha. Money is just a monetary obligation.
It's very— I always thought that concept wasn't about the power or
תוקף tokef of the individual statement but in this context it's sort
of framed that way. Like I can't make myself a רשע rasha
I always saw as kind of a way of protecting the individual
so to speak.
Well it is, but the bottom line is that the power of
admission is less. Okay so the גמרא Gemara says like this,
אלא מה לפיו Ella ma l'piv 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6,
7, 8, 9, 10,
11 lines from the bottom line starts to where הייתי פוטר, hayiti
poter, אלא מה לפיו שכן מחייבו חומש. Ella ma l'piv shekein mechayvo
chomesh. Okay
here's but nevertheless you can't say that witnesses are always stronger because
your own words can make you pay a— did I skip a
line? Hold on.
I skipped a line.
No I didn't. אלא מה לפיו שכן מחייבו אשם. Ella ma l'piv
shekein mechayvo asham. But wait a minute, your own admission can make
you bring an אשם asham and witnesses won't make you bring an
אשם. asham. So again you can't say witnesses are always better. So
the גמרא Gemara says אשם היינו קרבן. asham haynu korban. No, no,
no, we just said אשם asham is a type of a קרבן.
korban. So according to רבי מאיר, Rebbi Meir, witnesses would make you
bring an אשם asham the same way they'd make you bring a
חטאת. chatas. So again as long as we're working with רבי מאיר,
Rebbi Meir, witnesses are always stronger. Ah, here's a way in which—
but the גמרא Gemara says no you still can't say it. אלא
מה לפיו שכן מחייבו חומש. Ella ma l'piv shekein mechayvo chomesh.
Ah but your own admission makes you pay a fifth, remember we
just dealt with that in בבא קמא, Bava Kamma, you admit that
you swore falsely in the process of stealing money from somebody and
only when you admit do you pay a fifth. If witnesses show
you're lying, you don't pay a fifth. Okay, so here's a case
where
you can't say witnesses are always better. Here your admission makes you
pay a fifth in addition to what you stole and witnesses would
not. So the גמרא Gemara says הלא קשיא. halo kashya. That's not
a— that's not a problem. That doesn't show that witnesses are not
always stronger. רבי חייא כרבי מאיר סבירא ליה. Rebbi Chiya k'Rebbi Meir
sevira lei. We're again going to say that he's within the position
of רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir who gives this tremendous weight to witnesses
and says witnesses make you bring a קרבן. korban. So if witnesses
can make you bring a קרבן korban even without any acceptance of
guilt, guess what else witnesses can make you do without any acceptance
of guilt? Make you pay a חומש. chomesh. Okay? כי היכי דמחייבי
ליה קרבן מקל וחומר מחייבי ליה חומש מקל וחומר. Ki haichi d'mechayvei
lei korban m'kal vachomer mechayvei lei chomesh m'kal vachomer. Yeah,
you know what? Yes, we think about all these things as part
of accepting your guilt and responsibility and therefore you bring a קרבן,
korban, you pay a חומש, chomesh, it's all part of כפרה, kappara,
atonement, but רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir says witnesses are always stronger and
therefore they can make you bring a קרבן korban even if you
don't admit, they can make you pay a חומש chomesh even though
you don't admit. So within that approach it's almost becoming a little
bit of a tautology-just approach. You know, I'm going to say witnesses
are always stronger and anytime you show me that they're not I'm
going to say they are anyway. So if witnesses are always stronger,
then they should also make you make a שבועה shvua in this
case. this case of a hundred and fifty. So the גמרא Gemara
says no, there's still going to be a case where I'm going
to show you that witnesses are not always stronger than your own
admission. אלא מה לפיו שכן אין בו הכחש והזמה תאמר בעדים שיש
בהם הכחש והזמה. Ela ma lapiv sheken ein bo hachshash vehazama tomer
be'eidim sheyesh bam hachshash vehazama. When I do admit my own monetary
debt, you could prove that I'm lying and I still am believed
more than any contradictory witnesses. Okay, I say I borrowed from David
a hundred dollars on Monday at 12:00 PM and a thousand witnesses
come and say that I was with them on a cruise ship
at Monday at 1:00 PM. A thousand people come to court and
say it, it doesn't matter. Okay, הודאת בעל דין כמאה עדים דמי.
Hoda'at ba'al din kime'ah eidim dami. It's really more than מאה עדים
דמי. me'ah eidim dami. My own admission of a monetary liability trumps
any testimony against me because to some degree when I admit that
I owe David money, it's not really about the facts of the
case. The facts of the case might be that I was on
that cruise ship and I never borrowed a hundred dollars. But the
same way I could stick my hand in my pocket right now
and give him the hundred dollars, I can make a statement in
court that obligates me in the hundred dollars. Okay, so the reason
I'm believed against myself is you could just say no, I'm when
it comes to matters about me, I'm more believed than other people,
but I think it's really because when it comes to matters about
me, it's not about what actually happened. If I say I owe
David a hundred dollars, I owe David a hundred dollars. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says when it's my own admission, no contradiction will
be effective, no contrary עדים, eidim, no proof that I was somewhere
else, no testimony that it didn't happen. But witnesses can be contradicted
and proven to be somewhere else, הזמה, hazama, and can be thrown
out. Okay, so clearly there's one area in which witnesses are not
stronger than your own admission. One minute, the גמרא Gemara says אלא
מה לפיו שכן אין בו הכחש והזמה תאמר בעדים שיש בהם הכחש
והזמה. Ela ma lapiv sheken ein bo hachshash vehazama tomer be'eidim sheyesh
bam hachshash vehazama. So you cannot just say that witnesses are stronger
all the time, they're also going to make you make a שבועה
shavuah here because they are not all the time stronger. Yes, Charlie
had a question?
This is different from דין אין אדם משים עצמו רשע.
din ein adam mesim
atzmo rasha.
Yeah, this is all totally in ממונות. mamonot. Okay. Yeah, this is
all about monetary again. אין אדם משים עצמו רשע. Ein adam mesim
atzmo rasha. If I say that I have to pay a fine,
certainly if I say I did something deserving lashes or the death
penalty, not only you know my testimony doesn't even get off the
ground. But in monetary matters, it's not only am I believed, I'm
believed more than anything else. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says okay,
so you can't just say that we know witnesses are always stronger,
they'll make you make a שבועה. shavuah. אלא אתיא מעד אחד. Ela
atya me'eid echad. Okay, we'll make the קל וחומר kal vachomer from
an עד אחד. eid echad. What's the קל וחומר kal vachomer from
an עד אחד? eid echad? ומה עד אחד שאין מחייבו ממון מחייבו
שבועה. U'ma eid echad she'ein mechayvo mamon mechayvo shavuah. When a one
witness says I owe David a hundred dollars, I don't have to
pay, it's only one witness, but what do I have to do?
I have to swear to contradict the עד אחד. eid echad. So
if an עד אחד eid echad which is weak does not make
me pay, makes me make a שבועה, shavuah, עדים שמחייבים אותו ממון,
eidim shemechayvin oto mamon, two witnesses that would make me pay if
they said I owed money, אינו דין שמחייבים אותו שבועה, eino din
shemechayvin oto shavuah, it's more so that they have to make me
make a שבועה. shavuah. So that's going to be an easy קל
וחומר, kal vachomer, right? Why is it an easy קל וחומר? kal
vachomer? Because there's no question that two are better than one. Okay,
so right, if you compare witnesses to my own admission, you'll say
ah, here's a case where your own admission is stronger. But if
you compare two witnesses to one witness, two witnesses are always stronger
than one. So if one witness can make me make a שבועה,
shavuah, two witnesses can make me make a שבועה. shavuah. Okay, but
there's a big difference. What's the difference? One witness says I owe
a hundred dollars, I have to make a שבועה shavuah that I
don't. Two witnesses say I owe fifty and I have to make
a שבועה shavuah that I don't owe the other fifty. What's the
difference?
You got the case here? One witness says I owe a hundred
dollars. I have to make a שבועה shavuah I don't owe. So
if one witness can make me make a שבועה shavuah when he
says I owe a hundred dollars and I say I don't owe,
then when two witnesses say I owe fifty dollars, I should certainly
have to make a שבועה shavuah that I don't owe the other
fifty.
You're admitting that you owe fifty?
No, well I'm not admitting.
No, well you're going to have to pay the fifty.
Right, in the one witness, my שבועה shavuah stops the witness. Right?
It contradicts what the witness is saying. By the two witnesses, I
do pay the fifty that they testify to, and now I have
to make a שבועה shavuah on something else. So just because one
witness forces me to contradict his testimony doesn't mean when two witnesses
say I owe fifty, it means anything about the other fifty. Okay,
so let's take a look. The גמרא Gemara says no, ומה עד
אחד שאין מחייבו ממון מחייבו שבועה עדים שמחייבים אותו ממון אינו דין
שמחייבים אותו שבועה. u'ma eid echad she'ein mechayvo mamon mechayvo shavuah eidim
shemechayvin oto mamon eino din shemechayvin oto shavuah. No, מה לעד אחד
שכן על מה שהוא מעיד הוא נשבע. ma lei eid echad sheken
al ma shehu me'id hu nishba. No, by one witness you swear
because you're swearing against what the witness says and your שבועה shavuah
stops the witness. תאמר בעדים שעל מה שכפר הוא נשבע. Tomer be'eidim
she'al ma shekafar hu nishba. That doesn't prove to you that by
two witnesses you have to swear on the remainder. Okay, so what
they testify to you pay. How does that show you you have
to swear on the remainder? So אלא אמר רב פפא אתיא מגלגול
שבועה דעד אחד. Ela amar Rav Papa atya migilgul shavuah de'eid echad.
All right, it comes from a rolling שבועה. shavuah. A גלגול שבועה
gilgul shavuah is, you see people sometimes debate whether Judaism believes in
גלגול. gilgul. So here it does believe in גלגול, gilgul, okay? As
long as it's a גלגול שבועה gilgul shvua we believe in it.
גלגול gilgul means like a rolling, so there's an idea of גלגול
נשמות gilgul neshamot right, that somebody dies and the soul is reincarnated
and goes through different forms or whatever, so here the שבועה shvua
rolls, okay? How does the שבועה shvua roll? 'Cause if I can
get you to make one שבועה shvua in court, I can get
you to make any שבועה shvua I want. I can just throw
claim on top of claim and you'll have to make a שבועה
shvua about it.
They call that the transmigration of souls.
There you go, exactly. So
in the case of a שבועה, shvua, let's say an עד אחד
ed echad came and said I owe a hundred dollars. I'd have
to swear to contradict the עד אחד. ed echad. But now David,
who wants me to pay him money, says, ah, I got you
to make one שבועה shvua Dov, what that עד אחד ed echad
says. Now make a שבועה shvua about something else. You were denying
another debt of mine, a two-hundred dollar debt. Go make a שבועה
shvua on that. And I'd have to make a שבועה shvua once
he's got me to make one שבועה, shvua, I'd have to make
any other שבועה shvua he wants me to make, okay? Which is
why you really want to avoid making שבועות shvuot in
court. So, in that case, when I'm making that other שבועה shvua
on that other money, I'm not contradicting the witness. It's just a
pure שבועה shvua based on a pure claim. So if one witness
could indirectly lead to me making a שבועה shvua on something, okay,
right?
Here's one witness, okay? And he says I owe a hundred dollars,
okay, and I have to make a שבועה shvua to contradict it.
Okay? So then the case is, so when two witnesses,
right, say I owe fifty dollars,
okay, then I have to make a שבועה shvua
to contradict the other fifty. So the גמרא Gemara says that's not
relevant. Here your שבועה shvua contradicts, right? That doesn't prove that in
this case you have to make some different שבועה, shvua, right, a
שבועה shvua on the remaining fifty. But the גמרא Gemara says, ah,
but here,
after I've made the שבועה shvua that I contradict, I will have
to make any other שבועה shvua that he wants me to make,
okay? That's גלגול, gilgul, right? So if one witness can lead to
me making any type of שבועה, shvua, when two witnesses who are
stronger than one have me do one thing, it should certainly be
able to lead to me making a שבועה shvua on something else.
Okay, there's obviously though a difference. The reason here I make on
these other things is because the שבועה, shvua, we began with a
שבועה. shvua. That doesn't prove that here, when you don't begin with
a שבועה, shvua, that it can lead you to having to make
a שבועה shvua on something else, which is what the גמרא Gemara
responds. And the גמרא Gemara says, מה לגלגול שבועה דעד אחד שכן
שבועה גוררת שבועה.
Mah le'gilgul shvua de'ed
echad sheken shvua goreret shvua. No, by an עד אחד ed echad
שבועה, shvua, an עד
אחד ed echad
eventually can get you to make a שבועה shvua on other things,
but that's because one שבועה shvua drags other שבועות shvuot with it.
תאמר בעדים דממון קמחייבי. Tomar be'edim de'mamon kam'chaivei. In the case of
witnesses, they only make me pay fifty dollars. Just because I'm paying
fifty dollars, that doesn't prove I have to make a שבועה shvua
on something else. Are you with me?
But why in the case of the two עדים, edim, why is
the litigant making that other שבועה? shvua?
Because you said, you, the בעל דין, ba'al din, right?
You
said I owe a hundred. And I said here, I owe zero.
Right? Here that proves fifty, so I need to make a שבועה
shvua on the other fifty, because this testimony partly substantiated the
claim.
Whose authority am I making that שבועה shvua about the other fifty?
On the fact that the witnesses partly substantiated the claim.
You are forcing me to make that שבועה? shvua? Yeah.
But you can't prove it from this case because in this case
the שבועה shvua contradicts, or a שבועה shvua leads to a שבועה.
shvua. There's none of that here. I'm not contradicting them and it's
not that a שבועה shvua leads to a שבועה. shvua.
No, I get that, but what is common between these cases?
Yes, that's why we're trying to argue for it, but we haven't
proven it.
But it's not a good disproof. Exactly. It's the same situation where
two witnesses, a witness is coming and you're making a שבועה, shvua,
yes, in that case it happens to be contradicting it.
We're not proving that this isn't true, we're just saying you can't
prove that it is true. But the
dissimilarity... Listen. No, no, no. We're not proving you don't make one.
You are trying to make an argument that you do. How can
I prove that you have to make a שבועה shvua here? Because
you make a שבועה shvua here. Okay? And I'm saying just because
you make a שבועה shvua here doesn't prove this case. The reason
you make a שבועה shvua here is either because you're directly contradicting
the witness or because one שבועה shvua leads to a שבועה. shvua.
Does that prove that you make a שבועה shvua here? Can you
prove from this that you make a שבועה shvua here?
Two is better than one.
I see.
So but yes, they're better than one is why I'm paying the
fifty dollars, but that doesn't prove that I make a שבועה shvua
on the part that they're not testifying on.
So we're trying to kind of if you should make a שבועה
shvua in that case at all.
Right. This case I definitely pay fifty. You said fifty, I'm going
to pay fifty. Okay? But how does that prove that I need
to make the שבועה shvua on the other fifty?
Aren't those
עדים... edim...
No, that's what we're trying to prove. We know this 50 makes
me pay 50. What we don't know is whether it makes me
take a שבועה shvua on the other 50. Okay. Here we know
that this, sorry, we know
that this hundred-dollar testimony makes me
make, makes a שבועה.
shvua. And we know that this שבועה shvua leads to these other
שבועות. shvuos. Okay. Here the 50 makes me make a 50.
The question is why do I make that שבועה?
shvua? Do I make another שבועה? shvua? And the גמרא Gemara is
saying just because two is better than one doesn't prove it. Here
you had to start with contradicting and then that led to other
שבועות. shvuos. Here you start with paying. It doesn't prove that you
would make another שבועה. shvua.
Another way of asking, another way to see this deliberation is we
know he has to make a שבועה shvua in the case of
the two עדים, eidim, but why?
No, no, we do not know he has to make a שבועה.
shvua. We know he pays 50 bucks. We don't know he makes
a שבועה shvua on the other 50. Okay. All right. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says אלא אמר פפא אתיא מגולגול שבועה
דנחמיה. Ella amar Pappa asya migilgul shvua d'Nechemya. מה גלגול שבועה דנחמיה
שכן שבועה גוררת שבועה. Ma gilgul shvua d'Nechemya shekein shvua goreret shvua.
No,
you can't prove it by the fact that you make another שבועה
shvua here. That's because you started with a שבועה. shvua. So the
גמרא Gemara says תאמר בעדים דממונא קמחייב. Tomar b'eidim demamona kamichaiev. But
by the witnesses, you're paying money. Money won't necessarily lead to making
a שבועה shvua on the rest. פיו יוכיח. Piv yochiach. Okay. But
the case of your own admission will be a proof. By your
own admission, you admit to 50 and you make a שבועה shvua
on the rest. So if you have witnesses, you should make a
שבועה shvua on the rest. מה לפיו שכן אין בו הכחשה. Ma
l'piv shekein ein bo hachasha.
We just already showed that you can't assume witnesses are stronger than
my admission, because witnesses can be contradicted, my admission cannot. So the
גמרא Gemara says עד אחד יוכיח. Eid echad yochiach. Okay. That's proof
from עד אחד, eid echad, שיש בו הכחשה ומחייבו שבועה, sheyeish bo
hachasha umichaivo shvua, who can be contradicted and it makes me take
a שבועה. shvua. No. מה לעד אחד שכן על מה שהוא מעיד
נשבע תאמר בעדים שעל מה שהוא כופר הוא נשבע. Ma l'eid echad
shekein al mah shehu meid nishba tomar b'eidim she'al mah shehu kofer
hu nishba. No,
because by the עד אחד eid echad you do it to contradict
what he's saying. By your admission, by you know, by one עד
eid you're contradicting what the עד eid is saying. By עדים, eidim,
you're taking a שבועה shvua on the other thing. So the גמרא
Gemara says פיו יוכיח. Piv yochiach. Okay. Go back to your own
admission. וחזר הדין. V'chazar hadin. And it goes in a circle.
I'll diagram this on the board in a minute. לא ראי זה
כראי זה ולא ראי זה כראי זה. Lo rei zeh k'rei zeh
v'lo rei zeh k'rei zeh. The unique characteristics of one case are
not similar to those of the other. הצד השווה שבהם, Hatzad hashaveh
shebahem, the common denominator is שלטענת כפירה הן באין, sheletanat kefirah hen
bain, that they come as a result of a claim and a
counter-claim. ונשבע. Venishba. And you'll make an oath. אף אני אביא עדים
שלטענת כפירה הן באין ונשבע. Af ani avi eidim sheletanat kefirah hen
bain venishba. Similar by witnesses, there's a claim and a counter-claim, you
should make an oath. Now, let me just clarify that. I did
that a little quickly. Okay. So this is what I, I
just was a little, a little hasty. I know.
Anyway,
if you would stop asking all the questions, I'd go a little
slower. So, anyway,
here's one case of a שבועה, shvua, okay?
I'm a pedagogue move. I know, I know.
Here's one case of a שבועה. shvua. עד אחד, Eid echad, okay?
Another case of a שבועה shvua is I say okay, 50, okay,
I admit to 50. Okay.
I admit to 50. Right. You say 100.
You say 100. I admit to 50. Okay. And in that case,
that's פיו. piv. That's your classic מודה במקצת. modeh bimiktzat. This is
עד אחד. eid
echad. Okay. This up
here is עדים. eidim. This is our
question.
Okay. So I admit to 50 and therefore I take a שבועה
shvua on the other 50. I have to give you a שבועה
shvua on the other 50.
That's basically כפרה. kapara.
Okay. Right. So not, not כפרה, kapara, because you've partly substantiated the
claim. Okay. So here are two cases where you make a שבועה.
shvua. עד אחד Eid echad and מודה במקצת. modeh bimiktzat. And we're
going to try to prove from this the case of witnesses saying
50, I pay 50, I have to make a שבועה shvua on
the rest. So the גמרא Gemara says okay, you don't, you can't
prove it from מודה במקצת, modeh bimiktzat, because even though witnesses should
be better than my own admission, right, this is עדים, eidim, this
is פיו, piv, okay, this is פיו, piv, this is עדים. eidim.
So witnesses generally are better than my own admission, but there's a
place in which my own admission is stronger, that my own admission
can't be contradicted. So maybe just because my admission makes me pay,
maybe witnesses do not. Oh wait, עד אחד eid echad can be
contradicted and עד אחד eid echad makes me take a שבועה. shvua.
So then two witnesses should make me take a שבועה. shvua. No,
because the reason here he makes me take a שבועה shvua is
because I'm contradicting what he's saying. That doesn't prove that I take
a שבועה shvua on something other than they're saying. Oh, but this
is a case where you're taking a שבועה shvua on something other
than you admit. Okay. So this has the feature of a שבועה
shvua on the rest. Okay.
And but your פיו piv is
stronger.
This has a case of, this has a case of it's only
a שבועה shvua like on the testimony, it's not on the rest,
okay? So but the, but
the עד ed can be contradicted. So what the גמרא Gemara is
saying is, let's look at the move of the גמרא. Gemara. You
can't prove from here that you make a שבועה shvua in that
case because although it is the same thing, it's a שבועה shvua
on the rest of the claim, but this is weaker because your
test, your admission can't be contradicted. The, I mean, excuse me, this
is stronger, stronger. So maybe you only make a שבועה shvua here
and you don't make it there. Ah, but here it can be
contradicted, there is that, has that weakness, and nevertheless you make a
שבועה. shvua. Ah, but this is, but this is a שבועה shvua
on the testimony itself, not on the rest. Ah, but this is
a שבועה shvua on the rest. So what you do is what
you basically say is, and you know, don't tell me that each
one of these can't be compared because you sort of like just
look at the common denominator, okay? So if we remove the denominator,
one thing that's not similar is this, this is in common because
this can't be contradicted and this can, okay? This isn't common, this
is a שבועה shvua on the rest and this is a שבועה
shvua on the testimony. So there's no common denominator, okay? So what's
the rule? When do you make a שבועה? shvua? So you make,
so what the גמרא Gemara says, well, you make a שבועה shvua
when there's a claim and a counter-claim. Of course, that's crazy because
then in every case you should make a שבועה. shvua. So it
doesn't, no,
it means when there's a claim that's been somewhat substantiated. So in
this case the claim has been somewhat substantiated because of my admission.
In this claim, the case has been like somewhat substantiated or strengthened
because of the testimony of the עד. ed. So in this case
where there are two witnesses, it's also somewhat substantiated, I should have
to make a שבועה. shvua.
It goes back to the קשיא kashya you said four seconds ago.
That's every court case.
No, because if I just say you owe me money and you
say you don't for example,
that's not going to be a court case, or not a court
case.
Yeah, that's a כופר הכל, kofer hakol, maybe you'd have to make
a שבועה. shvua. That's a claim and a counter-claim.
No, no, no, that's basically, that's the one case when you're not
going to force a
שבועה, shvua, is the כופר הכל. kofer hakol. But if there's some
substantiation, so the classic case of it being substantiated is עד אחד
ed echad or my admission. So if this, this substantiates my claim,
and admission substantiates my claim, then two witnesses on part of the
claim also substantiates the claim, which is not a bad point, right?
Bottom line is you make a שבועה shvua when there's something to
back up your claim, the other guy makes a שבועה, shvua, okay?
So the fact that there are differences, here you only make it
to counter the witness, that doesn't prove you would make it against,
here though you do make it against, that's because maybe in some
ways your own admission is more powerful. Okay, but let's step back
and abstract. What seems to be the shape of it? The shape
of it seems to be, if you've got something to back up
your claim, either an עד אחד ed echad or a partial admission,
the guy has to make a שבועה. shvua. So when there are
two witnesses on part of it, the guy has to make a
שבועה. shvua.
All right, the bottom left, the bottom left section is that's a
כופר הכל kofer hakol with
an עד אחד ed echad to back it up.
Yeah, to back it up.
But if there's no עד אחד, ed echad, it wouldn't be a
שבועה. shvua. All right, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this,
if I denied the entire amount.
All right, the entire claim. All right, all right, let's move on.
All right, that was, that was complicated, we're going to move on.
Okay, okay,
the גמרא Gemara says, no, there's still a way in which the
two witnesses is worse than the other two cases and there shouldn't
be a שבועה. shvua. The גמרא Gemara says like this, מה לצד
השוה שבהן שכן הוחזק כפרן. ma letzad hashava shebahen sheken huchzak kafran.
No,
no, no. In the other two cases there's not evidence that you're
a liar, okay? One witness says I'm lying, I admit it to
part, there's no evidence that I'm a liar. Since there's no evidence
that I'm a liar, I'm a denier, I can make a שבועה
shvua on the rest. Maybe my שבועה shvua will do some good.
But תאמר בעדים שכן הוחזק כפרן? tomar be'edim sheken huchzak kafran? Ah,
the גמרא Gemara says fine. The rule is something to back up
the other guy's claim, I have to make a שבועה. shvua. But
here I said I owed nothing, witnesses proved I owed fifty. They're
proving that I'm a liar, right? Everybody get that in that case?
So there's evidence that I'm a liar. Once there's evidence that I'm
a liar, why should we think a שבועה shvua will do any
good? All right, so okay, so the גמרא Gemara says one minute,
just because they're, just because they're proving I'm a liar doesn't mean
I'm a liar. Okay,
so ובעדים הוחזק כפרן? u'be'edim huchzak kafran? Just because there are witnesses
that say I do owe fifty when I said I owe zero,
that doesn't prove that I'm a, כפרן kafran is not just a
liar, I was a liar but I'm a denier, I'm denying my
obligation. ואמר רבי אבין אמר רב חסדא הכל במלוה כשר לעדות. ve'amar
Rabbi Avin amar Rav Chisda hakol be'milve kasher le'edut. If I deny
that I owe you money and witnesses prove that I'm lying, I'm
still a כשר לעדות. kasher le'edut. I can't, you know, it's not
like, oh, now I'm a גזלן, gazlan, a גזלן gazlan is a
פסול לעדות. pasul le'edut. No, if I admitted that, we'll see in
a minute. Even though I was lying, I'm not necessarily a גזלן.
gazlan. בפיקדון, be'pikadon, but if you said where's my iPhone you asked
me to watch and I said what iPhone, okay then and witnesses
prove that I have had it, פסול עדות, pasul edut, I'm פסול.
pasul. So what's the difference? The difference is the following: is that
if I'm denying that I have your iPhone, the only reason I'm
denying it is because I'm trying to keep it to myself. If
I'm denying that I have your $100, I might be planning on
paying you back, but remember we discussed yesterday, I just don't have
the cash on me and I need to push you off to
get my, buy myself some time. So just because I denied it,
I lied about it, doesn't mean that I was going to steal
it. Okay, but by the actual concrete object that I was watching,
if I was denying it, and now it would have to be
that it hadn't been lost. Maybe I lost the iPhone and I
was looking for it. If we could prove that I knew where
the iPhone was and I was denying it, in that case, right,
I am, I am פסול עדות pasul edut because I'm clearly stealing.
So the גמרא Gemara says, look, you're right. When you can substantiate
a claim, you make a שבועה, shvua, so here it's been partially
substantiated so you make a שבועה, shvua, but once he's proven a
thief and a liar, we shouldn't allow the שבועה. shvua. And the
גמרא Gemara says, even though he's been proven a liar, it's, he's
not a thief. He might just be trying to buy time to
give the money back.
Okay, so it's not, we can't translate כפרן kafran as, it's like
several, it's different nuances of lies.
Right, that's why I said it doesn't mean liar.
It means, so lying to the first degree is
no, no, it's not about how bad of a lie it was.
It's about whether you're trying to, whether you're trying to deny the
obligation, whether you're trying to steal the money is really what it
boils down to. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay,
אלא פרכא
הכי, ella parcha hachi, fine. So until, so you've sort of proven
your case. It's not exactly a קל וחומר kal vachomer anymore, but
your argument is we look at the cases where you make a
שבועה, shvua, it's, your claim has been substantiated. Here too you should
make a שבועה, shvua, the claim has been substantiated. The guy is
not necessarily a thief, so שבועה shvua is relevant. So רבי חייא
Rabbi Chiya makes a good argument. You should make, have to make
a שבועה shvua in the case of witnesses substantiating part of the
claim. So if we've got a problem with רבי חייא, Rabbi Chiya,
it's the, it's the following. Even in פיקדון pikadon פסול עדות?
pasul edut? What? Yeah, פיקדון pikadon you'd be פסול עדות.
pasul edut. Yeah, yeah, I read that. אלא פרכא הכי, ella parcha
hachi, here's how you should read it. Here's a question against רבי
חייא, Rabbi Chiya, maybe he's right, okay, wait, let's look in the
גמרא. Gemara. פרכא הכי, parcha hachi, מה לצד השווה שבהן שכן אינן
בתורת הזמה, תאמר בעדים שישנן בתורת הזמה. ma latsad hashaveh shebahen sheken
einan betorat hazama, tomar be'edim sheyeshnan betorat hazama. Now
this is a much weaker challenge. Here, even if people can be
contradicted, like this עד אחד ed echad can be contradicted, if this
עד אחד ed echad is proven to be a liar, he doesn't
pay any fine in בית דין. Beit Din. The idea of עדים
זוממים, edim zomemim, כאשר זמם לעשות לאחיו, ka'asher zamam la'asot le'achiv, is
only by two witnesses. It's not by one witness, because that really,
that really emerges from the strength of two witnesses. Since two witnesses
can force the payment or the punishment, therefore if they're lying, the
punishment is done to them. It doesn't apply to one witness who
can't force the payment. But nevertheless, although it really emerges from the
strength of theirs, the גמרא Gemara is saying is maybe that's a
weakness. These two witnesses are, are vulnerable to the punishments of הזמה.
hazama. That's not true in these cases. So maybe because of that
"weakness", it's a very little weakness, maybe that should mean that you
shouldn't have to pay in this case. That's a weakness that exists
in this case that doesn't exist in the others. Okay? So the
גמרא Gemara says, הא לא קשיא, ha lo kashya, that's not difficult.
רבי חייא תורת הזמה לא פריך. Rabbi Chiya torat hazama lo parich.
Yeah, רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya doesn't think that's a question. Okay? Which
basically means they can be contradicted, the fact that the witnesses have
to pay emerges from a strength of the witness, it can't be
argued to be a weakness of the witness. All right, so we've
made a good argument that based on common denominator, when your claim
is, is substantiated to some degree, the other side has to swear.
It's true by עד אחד, ed echad, it's true by מודה במקצת.
modeh bemiktzat. This is actually a nice little diagram, because these are
the classic cases of when a שבועה shvua exists outside of שומרים.
shomrim. Your claim is backed by an עד אחד ed echad or
you admit to part of it. So the common denominator is there's
something that has come to substantiate the claim. So similarly, if witnesses
testify to part of it, you should also make a שבועה. shvua.
That's רבי חייא's Rabbi Chiya argument, that's a very reasonable argument. And
the גמרא Gemara says fine, maybe he's right, you do make a
שבועה shvua in that case. But here's our problem. The גמרא Gemara
says
אלא דקאמר, ella de'ka'amar, our problem is not with that argument, that
thing, statement that you make a שבועה. shvua. The problem is his
attempt to connect it to our משנה, Mishna, because that has nothing
to do with our משנה. Mishna. Okay? אלא דקאמר ותנא טונא, ella
de'ka'amar vetana tuna, when he wanted to find support to that idea
from our משנה. Mishna. מי דמי? mi dami? How is it comparable
to the case of the טלית? tallit? Remember the case of the
טלית, tallit, how long it's been. מי דמי, התם למלוה אית ליה
סהדי, ללוה לית ליה
סהדי, דלא מסיק ליה ולא מידי. mi dami, hatam lemalveh it leh
sahade, leloveh leit leh sahade, delo masik leh velo midi. In the
case of
the what do you call
it, the,
right, one minute.
Right, in the case of the 100 and the 50, the מלוה
malveh has witnesses, the מלוה malveh has witnesses that he owes 50,
and the לוה loveh has no, doesn't. The לוה Loveh doesn't have
witnesses that he doesn't owe money, right? The מלווה Malve says 100.
The לוה Loveh says nothing. The מלווה Malve has witnesses 50. The
לוה Loveh has no contradictory witnesses. The לוה Loveh has no witnesses
to back his case. The לוה Loveh לית ליה סהדי Leit lei
sahadi לא מסקי ביה ולא מידי. Lo maskei bei velo midi. The
לוה Loveh doesn't have witnesses that he doesn't owe money. והוה ליה
סהדי, Ve-hava lei sahadi, if the לוה Loveh had witnesses דלא מסקי
ביה ולא מידי De-lo maskei bei velo midi that he didn't owe
money, לא בעי רבי חייא לאשתבועי. Lo ba'i Rabbi Chiyya le-ishtabuyei. Rabbi
Chiyya wouldn't ask him to swear. Right, so the reason he swears
here is there's witnesses to back this guy's claim and this poor
guy has no witnesses, so he's got to take an oath. How
can that be comparable to the case of the טלית? Tallit? הכא,
Hacha, the way we wanted to say with the case of the
טלית Tallit was what? David and I are holding on to this
טלית, Tallit, so I say it's all mine, I'm essentially saying to
David you owe me $100, you owe me the whole
טלית, Tallit, and David says no I don't, it's all mine, so
he's denying my claim. And the fact that I'm holding on to
it proves that 50, that half of it is mine, that he
owes me 50. That's like עדים Edim that he owes me 50.
But he says but that's not Rabbi Chiyya, that's not similar, because
David has just as much witnesses to back up his claim as
I have to back up my claim. His holding on to it
proves that he owes that I owe him the other 50.
הכי קאמר, Hachi ka'amar, the case of שנים אוחזין Shenayim Ochazin is
each one has a witness.
Each one has equal standing. Exactly. So the גמרא Gemara says הכא
כי היכי דאנן סהדי בהאי, Hacha ki heichi de-anan sahadi be-hai, the
same way we have witnesses that this guy deserves 50, אנן סהדי
בהאי, Anan sahadi be-hai, we have witnesses the other guy deserves 50.
So you might be right that in this case he makes a
שבועה, Shevuah, but that has nothing to do with our
משנה. Mishna. אלא כי אתמר דתניא תניא אידך דרבי חייא אתמר, Ella
ki itmar de-tanya tanya idach de-Rabbi Chiyya itmar, fine. We wanted to
use our משנה Mishna not to illustrate this teaching of Rabbi Chiyya
about the witnesses and making a שבועה Shevuah on the rest, but
to illustrate another teaching of Rabbi Chiyya. What was the other teaching
of Rabbi Chiyya? דאמר רבי חייא, De-amar Rabbi Chiyya, another variation of
מודה במקצת. Modeh be-miktzat. מנה לי בידך, Maneh li beyadcha, David, you
owe me $100. והלה אומר אין לך בידי אלא חמשים זוז, Ve-haleh
omer ein lecha beyadi ella chamishim zuz, I only owe you 50,
והילך, Ve-heilech, and here it is, get out of my face, here's
the 50 bucks. Now here's a question. Is he a מודה במקצת
Modeh be-miktzat or not? Do we say I said 100, he says
50, he has to take an oath on the other 50? Or
do we say as soon as he handed me the 50 right
at that moment,
he really like eliminated that part of the conversation and now it's
just I say you owe me 50 and he says he doesn't
and he's really a כופר הכל Kofer ha-kol on $50? When he
hands over the money immediately once he admits to it, does it
really sort of you know separate the claims? Says this is off
the table, here's your money, get out of here. So now what
I'm left with is saying you owe me 50 and he says
I don't owe you 50 and it's a כופר הכל. Kofer ha-kol.
So is it a מודה במקצת Modeh be-miktzat if he pays me
off the amount that he admits to right away? You understand the
question? All right,
נחזי. Nechezi. מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? Rabbi Chiyya says חייב, Chayav, it
is a מודה במקצת. Modeh be-miktzat. מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? והילך נמי
כמודה במקצת הטענה דמי. Ve-heilech nami ke-modeh be-miktzat ha-ta'ana dami. It doesn't
really explain it, but okay. Yes, even when he says take the
50, at that moment he admitted to part and it's still a
מודה במקצת. Modeh be-miktzat. דתניא תונא, De-tanya tuna, what's the support? שנים
אוחזין בטלית. Shenayim Ochazin be-Tallit. How is the case of two people
holding it
up support? הכא כיון דתפיס, Hacha keivan de-taphis, so I say David
the whole טלית Tallit is mine, ואנן סהדי דמאי דתפיס והילך הוא,
Ve-anan sahadi de-mai de-taphis ve-heilech hu, and witnesses are saying that effectively
witnesses the evidence is that half of it is mine. So that's
like David is saying take half.
So now I'm just arguing on the other half and he's denying
it and
הוא משתבע, Hu mishtava, he has to take a שבועה. Shevuah. Now
everybody should realize that we just pulled the wool over your eyes
because
the טלית Tallit over your eyes, I messed that opportunity. We just
got through saying that there's no way of framing this as a
מודה במקצת Modeh be-miktzat because any claim I have against David and
proof I have against David, he has the equal claim and proof
against me because we're both holding on to the טלית. Tallit. The
גמרא Gemara is going to get back to that but what the
point is is if for a moment we could have a suspension
of disbelief and accept the idea that this is somewhat like a
מודה במקצת, Modeh be-miktzat, then the point is he's still making a
שבועה Shevuah even though effectively he's already paying off half his claim.
The fact that I'm holding half is like he's already given me
that half and nevertheless there's still a שבועה, Shevuah, so that should
be evidence that the idea that even with a והילך Ve-heilech type
of a response there's still a
שבועה. Shevuah. We're going to circle back to this. רב ששת אמר,
Rav Sheshet amar, now רב ששת Rav Sheshet would say והילך פטור.
Ve-heilech patur. No, by והילך Ve-heilech you're exempt. מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama?
כיון דאמר ליה והילך, Keivan de-amar lei ve-heilech, once he says והילך,
Ve-heilech, הני זוזי דקא מודה בגוייהו כמאן דנקיט להו מלווה דמי, Hanei
zuzzei de-ka modeh be-gavaihu ke-man de-nakit lehu malve dami, the money that
he admits to is like it's already in the מלווה's Malve pocket.
ואינך חמשים, Ve-inach chamishim, and the other
50, הא לא מודה ליה, Ha lo modeh lei, he's not admitting
it, והוה ליה כופר הכל Ve-hava lei kofer ha-kol on the other
50. הלכך ליכא הודאת מקצת הטענה. Hilchach leika hoda'at miktzat ha-ta'ana. There's
not a partial admission. ולרב ששת U-le-Rav Sheshet says the גמרא, Gemara,
according to רב ששת, Rav Sheshet, קשיא. Kashya.
What do you do with our מתניתין *matnisin*? That's a case of
הילך heilech. *helech* and you make a שבועה shvuah. *shvu'ah*. So the
answer is obvious. אמר לך רב ששת *amar lach Rav Sheshet*, רב
ששת *Rav Sheshet* will say to you, מתניתין *matnisin*, our משנה mishna.
*Mishna*, that's not a מודה במקצת modeh be-miktsat. דאורייתא שבועה shvuah *modeh
bimiktzat d'Oraita shvu'ah*. מתניתין תקנת חכמים היא *matnisin Takkanat Chachamim hi*.
That's a רבנן *rabanan* שבועה shvuah. *shvu'ah*. Either to stop people from
grabbing טליתות *tallitot* or to get more evidence on the table, but
that is not a מודה במקצת modeh be-miktsat. *modeh bimiktzat*. And here
רש"י *Rashi* and תוספות *Tosafot* jump in, and you know how we
know it's not a מודה במקצת modeh be-miktsat, *modeh bimiktzat*? Because of
what we said before, because David has just as much evidence as
I do. Any testimony I have, he has opposite testimony. So of
course it's not a מודה במקצת modeh be-miktsat. *modeh bimiktzat*. We just
got through saying that. So how can you try to bring that
as evidence about some הילך heilech *helech* claim? Alright, is that clear?
Yes? Jenna, no?
That's basically the point. We tried to structure it as a type
of מודה במקצת modeh miketzat *modeh bimiktzat*. I say—not a מודה במקצת
modeh miketzat *modeh bimiktzat*—עדים eidim, במקצת *edim bimiktzat*. I say you owe
me a hundred, I have עדים *edim* that I have half, right?
And essentially you're giving me the half because it's like there's a
הילך heilech *helech*, but the whole point is—but the whole response is,
but that's equal and opposite on the other side. Right, which is
what we said before. Yeah, okay, you're right, there's no admission of
מקצת *miktzat*. It's like the עדים *edim* of מקצת *miktzat*. Right.
Okay, same thing by the טלית *tallis*. Yes, same thing by the
hundred fifty-fifty.
I understand, I was using hundred fifty-fifty to read it into the
טלית *tallis*. I'm sorry. In the case of the טלית *tallis*, it's
not a מודה במקצת *modeh bimiktzat*, it's—as we were saying before—it's an
עדים במקצת *edim bimiktzat*. Okay, I say you owe me the whole
טלית *tallis*, you deny it, I have עדים *edim* that you owe
me half. That—so we're trying to argue that's a type of a
מודה במקצת *modeh bimiktzat* case. Okay, and with a הילך heilech. *helech*,
because the עדים *edim* makes it that half of it is—that I'm
entitled to it. Okay, but the response is you cannot begin to
talk about that like as an עדים במקצת מודה במקצת *edim bimiktzat
modeh bimiktzat* because the other side has the equal evidence in the
opposite direction, like we said before. Okay, right. So I'm sorry if
I was using the term—whatever—I mean עדים במקצת *edim bimiktzat*, but it
means a type of a מודה במקצת *modeh bimiktzat*. Alright, so anyway,
so רב ששת *Rav Sheshet* says give me a freaking break. Okay,
he did say exactly those words. That was in the גמרא Gemara.
*Gemara*. Okay, he says, you know, he says what do you mean
הילך heilech *helech*? It doesn't even start to be a עדים במקצת
מודה במקצת *edim bimiktzat modeh bimiktzat* like we said before, it's equal
proof on both sides. So the whole thing is a תקנת חכמים
*Takkanat Chachamim*. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says...
ואידך *ve'idach*, what would רב חייא *Rav Chiya* say back? אין תקנת
חכמים היא *in Takkanat Chachamim hi*. Yeah, you're right, of course it's
a תקנת חכמים *Takkanat Chachamim*. Okay, of course it's not a normal
עדים במקצת מודה במקצת *edim bimiktzat modeh bimiktzat*. That goes without saying.
We had to say it, but it goes without saying. Okay, מיהו
אי אמרת בשלמא מדאורייתא הילך heilech חייב chayav, *mihu i amarta bishlama
mid'Oraita helech chayav*. If you would say biblically by a real case
of מודה במקצת *modeh bimiktzat* even after you said הילך heilekh *helech*
you could still make a שבועה shvuah. *shvu'ah* on the rest, מתקני
רבנן שבועה shvuah. כעין דאורייתא *matkinay
rabanan shvu'ah k'ein d'Oraita*. The Rabbis would make a שבועה shvu'ah *shvu'ah*
parallel to a דאורייתא *d'Oraita*. אלא אי אמרת מדאורייתא הילך פטור heilech
patur? *ella
i amarta mid'Oraita helech patur*. But if biblically once you admitted to
part you would never be making a שבועה shvu'ah, *shvu'ah* on the
rest because the rest would be like a כופר הכל kofer ha-kol.
*kofer hakol*. So מתקני רבנן שבועה shvu'ah דלית דכוותה בדאורייתא *matkinay rabanan
shvu'ah d'laise d'chvassa bid'Oraita*? Would the Rabbis ever make something that there's
no biblical parallel to? So the basic point is like you're right.
The טלית *tallis* case is not really an עדים במקצת *edim bimiktzat*
or a מודה במקצת *modeh bimiktzat* because the same way I have
עדים *edim*, you have עדים *edim*, right? Like we said before. But
here's the point. Yes, it's all רבנן *rabbinic*. Fine. But if in
a comparable case in the תורה *Torah*, once I say take the
fifty dollars, the remainder I don't have to make a שבועה shvu'ah.
*shvu'ah* on because the remainder is basically like a כופר הכל kofer
ha-kol. *kofer hakol*. So shouldn't we say the same thing in this
case of the טלית *tallis*? Once I have proof that half is
mine and you have proof that half is yours and it's like
I'm already holding onto my half, like you're already holding onto your
half, shouldn't we say don't make a שבועה shvu'ah *shvu'ah* on the
rest because everything else—like the rest is off the table? You know
what—so that's the argument. The argument is yes, we're not saying it's
an עדים במקצת *edim bimiktzat* or מודה במקצת *modeh bimiktzat*, but we're
saying is that if in general what הילך heilekh. *helech* does is
it says the part that you're giving is done with and then
the rest is like a כופר הכל kofer ha-kol *kofer hakol* type
of a case. So we should say the same by the טלית
*tallis*. It's like you already have your half of the טלית *tallis*,
I already have my half of the טלית *tallis*, the rest of
our claims are
not like—you know—should not have a שבועה shvu'ah *shvu'ah* that comes as
a response to that. Alright, don't worry too much about the comparison
to the מתניתין *matnisin*. What we're going to be doing right now
is just discussing the הילך heilekh. *helech* question. When I say I
owe you money and you admit to part and you say הילך
heilekh. *helech*, is it a מודה במקצת *modeh bimiktzat* or is it
a כופר הכל kofer ha-kol *kofer hakol*? Alright, let's take a look.
מיתיבי *meisivei*, I ask you on this. אוי שלשים דינרין *oy
sheloshim dinarin*. So you've got a שטר shtar *shtar*, alright? I know
it was all very complicated, but focus now on the הילך heilekh.
*helech* question, not on whether it's comparable to the מתניתין *matnisin*. Comparable
to the מתניתין *matnisin* is a side point. Okay, so you have
a שטר shtar. *shtar*. My שטר shtar. *shtar* here says
Jenna borrowed from Dove on—on Monday, whatever, January 1st,
dollars.
That's what it said. It actually borrowed from me dollars. dollars. Okay?
So שנים or it says in דינרים dinarim or she borrowed from
me דינרי. dinarei. It says actually 'by 2'.
So how many?
So מהו אומר mahu omer חמש. chamesh. I say yes, she borrowed
five dollars from me, we forgot to write in the word five.
The לוה אומר שלש loveh omer shalosh and Jenna says no, no,
no, I only borrowed three dollars. Now if Jenna was really smart
or if she was lying, she would have said two. Right? You
understand? Because she said three. Does that give her more credibility? Or
the flip of giving her more credibility is that it makes her
a מודה במקצת. Okay, so we'll get to that, but you got
it, she could have said two. All right? So רבן שמעון בן
אלעזר אומר הואיל והודה במקצת הטענה ישבע. Rabban Shimon ben Elazar omer
ho'il ve-hodeh be-miktsat ha-ta'anah yishava. Jenna admitted to part. Now it sounds
like saying two would have been denying because it sort of goes
for granted that she owes me already two dollars. The question is,
does she owe me anything more than two dollars? Right? Everybody with
me here? Why two? Because it says she owes me dollars. The
שטר shtar. says she owes me dollars. Okay? So she clearly owes
me at least two dollars.
So when I say five, what I'm really saying is you owe
me three more than is obvious in the שטר. shtar, And she
says no, I only owe you one more than is obvious in
the שטר. shtar So she's a מודה במקצת. She'll take a שבועה.
shvu'ah? Okay?
So ישבע. yishava. So no good deed goes unpunished. רבי עקיבא אומר
אינו אלא כמשיב אבידה ופטור. Rabbi Akiva omer eino ella ke-meshiv aveidah
u-patur. No, no, no. It's like she's returning a lost object. We
have a general principle that if you return a lost object, you
can't the guy can't force you to take oaths about how you
treated it or whatever because then nobody would return a lost object.
Okay? So רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says it's similar here. She could
have just easily blown me off and said two. She giving me
that extra third was like returning a lost object. She could have
easily gotten away with it. Okay? And therefore I cannot impose a
שבועה shvu'ah on her. Which well, it'll actually a little bit it
sounds like רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva agrees in principle that it is
a מודה במקצת, but it's counterproductive to make her make a שבועה.
shvu'ah. It's counter, you know, societal policy to make her make a
שבועה. shvu'ah. But the other way of reading רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
is he's not saying it's a תקנה takanah to free her from
a שבועה. shvu'ah. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva saying is like yeah, she
you know, it's a מיגו. migo. She could have denied the whole
thing, so we should assume she's telling the truth. Okay? All right.
What you're saying is it's like your lost object meaning you didn't
take care of it's your fault for not making a loan document
that's clear.
Right? I mean, I'm not sure if he's blaming me, but he's
certainly saying like you gave me something that I didn't have a
right to expect I would get, you know. Okay? All right. רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva okay. So תניא מיהא רבן שמעון בן אלעזר אומר
הואיל והודה במקצת הטענה ישבע. tanya mi-ha Rabban Shimon ben Elazar omer
ho'il ve-hodeh be-miktsat ha-ta'anah yishava. רבי שמעון בן אלעזר Rabbi Shimon ben
Elazar says, look, Jenna admitted to part, she has to take an
oath. טעמא דאמרה שלש. ta'ama de-amrah shalosh. The reason is because she
said three. הא שתים פטור. ha shtayim patur. If she said two,
she'd be exempt. Now, why is she exempt if she says two?
I still say you owe me five, she said she owes me
two, right? Why is she exempt? The only reason she's exempt is
because we already know two. So two is sort of like a
הילך. heilekh Admitting two is not admitting to anything, because that money
was already effectively given to me. It was obvious in the שטר.
shtar So if that's true, that shows you that הילך heileich makes
it like a כופר הכל. הילך heileich, takes the money off the
table. Okay?
הא שתים פטור והאי שטר דקמודי ביה הילך הוא. ha shtayim patur
ve-hai shtar de-kamodi beih heilech hu. So the שטר, shtar if she
would have said two, is like הילך. heileich And therefore, admitting two
is not admitting. Admitting two, we already know two. That's off the
table. So and it would have been a כופר הכל. שמע מינה
הילך פטור. shma minah heilech patur. So you see הילך heileich is
exempt. When you give the money right up front, it takes it
off the table and you're left with a כופר הכל and you're
exempt. לא. lo. No, says the גמרא. Gemara לעולם אימא לך שתים
חייב. le-olam eima lach shtayim chayav. Two, actually רבי שמעון בן אלעזר
Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar would say even if Jenna said two, she'd
be חייב, chayav? which is pretty amazing because it would be like
a מודה במקצת. והאי דקתני שלש, ve-hai de-katani shalosh, so why did
he say three you're חייב? chayav לאפוקי
מדרבי עקיבא דאמר משיב אבידה הוי ופטור. le-apokei mi-de-Rabbi Akiva de-amar meshiv
aveidah havei u-patur. To show you that you might think two you're
חייב chayav. and three you're פטור, patur, because three you're doing a
צדקה, tsedakah, you're giving an extra one that you didn't have to
admit to. So maybe you should be like a משיב אבידה ופטור.
meshiv aveidah u-patur. קמשמע לן דהודה במקצת הטענה הוי וחייב. ka mashma
lan de-hodeh be-miktsat ha-ta'anah havei ve-chayav. Even three, you're it's a partial
admission and you're חייב. chayav. But maybe he would say two is
also seen as a partial admission and you're חייב. chayav. So the
גמרא Gemara does not buy this. אי הכי, ei hachi, if that's
true, רבן שמעון בן אלעזר אומר הואיל והודה במקצת הטענה ישבע. Rabban
Shimon ben Elazar omer ho'il ve-hodeh be-miktsat ha-ta'anah yishava. רבן שמעון בן
אלעזר Rabban Shimon ben Elazar's statement is: because she admitted to part,
she has to make an oath. Makes it sound like only because
she said three was it a partial admission. And if two also
was considered a partial admission, he should have said it in a
different way. He should have said אף זה ישבע מיבעי ליה. af
zeh yishava mibaei leih. Not only is two a partial admission, even
three is a partial admission and should not be considered to be
צדקה tsedakah and משיב אבידה. meshiv aveidah. But he doesn't say even
three you make an oath. He says three is a partial admission
and you make an oath. So it seems very clear that two
is not treated, two is not a partial admission. So if two
is not a partial admission, doesn't this prove that הילך heileich פטור?
patur? That הילך is a כופר הכל and is פטור? patur. So
the גמרא Gemara says... אלא לעולם
שתים פטור. Ella le'olam shtayim patur. Fine, fine, two you're exempt. But
nevertheless הילך חייב. chayav You're still חייב chayav. in a case of
הילך. This is a case that is different than הילך. Why? דשאני
הכא דקא מסייע ליה שטרא, De-shani hakha de-ka mesaye'a lei shtar'a, because
here generally if she were to say two, it's not an admission
of two. Like first of all there's two points. Number one is
the שטר shtar that says dollars without an amount should be read
in its minimalist way. And therefore when she says two she's just
saying exactly what the שטר shtar says. So number one, right, the
reason she shouldn't have to take a שבועה shvu'ah. on the rest
should be because her claim is backed up by the witnesses. Or
another way of saying, right, the reason... so why should she have
to take a witness? I say you owe me five, she says
I owe you two. The שטר shtar says dollars, it means two.
So that is effectively backed up, her claim is backed up by
witnesses. So that's why she doesn't make a שבועה, shvua not because
of הילך. Or another way of saying it is before we even
started debating the case in court the first two dollars were off
the table. We all knew the two dollars were minimally what she
was obligated, right? There was evidence of those two dollars. So that's
very different than when we come to court, we have no evidence
of anything, he admits to something and hands me the money. Right?
That could be a partial admission. But when there's... the שטר shtar
says she owes me part of it, right, that makes it a
very different type of a case. Are people with me or have
I lost everybody? So what is...
is שטר shtar equals... תוקף tokef as witnesses? Yes. Yes. That was
my question. Yes. Equivalent of two witnesses. Two witnesses.
Right. Right. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara, says like this, okay, אינמי
Inami משום דהוה ליה... mishum de-havei lei...
now here that's the simplest reason. The reason two is no שבועה
shvua. here has nothing to do with הילך. It's because two starts
being off the table because there's a שטר shtar even before any
exchange of arguments. And or B, the שטר shtar backs up the
claim of two, so that's why there's no שבועה. shvua. But now
the גמרא Gemara turns to a more technical reason. And what's the
more technical reason there's no שבועה shvua when it says two? אינמי,
Inami, says the גמרא, Gemara משום דהוה ליה שטר שיעבוד קרקעות ואין
נשבעין על כפירת שיעבוד קרקעות. mishum de-havei lei shtar shibud karka'ot ve-ein
nishba'in al kfirot shibud karka'ot. Okay, because the שטר shtar says dollars,
okay, with a שטר shtar. comes a שיעבוד shibud on land. So
I have a שיעבוד shibud on Jenna's land, okay? Now, how much?
Even if Jenna borrowed a thousand dollars from me, and even if
I could prove it because I get the witnesses here, I get
Charlie and David to testify, but the שטר shtar. just says dollars.
So you know how much of a שיעבוד shibud I have on
her land... she owes me a thousand, but you know how much
of a שיעבוד shibud I have on her land? For how much?
Two dollars? Two dollars.
Because the only thing that can be proven from the שטר shtar,
is two dollars. So the שיעבוד shibud is based on the שטר.
shtar So the amount she owes me is based on how much
she borrowed. So if I can prove from Charlie and David she
borrowed a thousand, she owes me a thousand. But if I want
to go collect her property that was sold to other people, I
only have a two dollar שיעבוד shibud because that's the only amount
that can be proven from the שטר. shtar You with me here?
Okay. So now I come to Jenna and I say Jenna you
owe me a thousand dollars, here's the שטר, it says dollars. She
says look at that, we forgot to write the number, haha. Okay,
so I only owe you two dollars. Now, the reason she doesn't
take a שבועה shvua. might have nothing to do with הילך or
anything. You know why she might not have to take a שבועה?
shvua. I said a thousand, she admitted to two. The part she
admitted to was money that had a שיעבוד, shibud, that had a
lien attached to it. So that's like admitting to land. And you
might remember from other places like we dealt with in בבא קמא,
Bava Kamma, things relating to land, land isn't stolen, land isn't whatever.
Well, here's another interesting הלכה halakha about land. You don't take an
oath and a שבועה shvua about land. Not only do you not
take an oath that you don't owe land, even if Jenna is
denying nine hundred and ninety eight dollars, but she's admitting to two
dollars of land, the admission part, if that's just about land, it's
not considered an admission. Okay? So when I say you owe me
a thousand and she says I only owe you two, she's only
admitting to
two dollars of שיעבוד shibud which are associated with land. That הלכתא,
hilkheta, that's like a technicality, and that's not considered an admission that
can lead to a שבועה. shvua Now, if she said she owed
me three, then she's saying admitting to two dollars of land and
one dollar of cash. So her one dollar of cash admission plus
what she's denying does lead to a שבועה. shvua. But if the
whole admission is about land, or the whole denial is about land,
no שבועה. So when she says two, her admission completely consists of
land and there's no שבועה. Yes Jenna?
Can you force me to pay the thousand dollars from land instead
that I have?
Yes.
But it's not necessarily land because it could be
cash, it could be other things. Right. Yes, yes, if that's the
only property you have, absolutely. Okay, so that's why. איכא דמתני לה
מסיפא. Ika de-matni lah mi-seifa. Now some have the same discussion but
starting from רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. We're just going to get to
this. איכא דמתני לה מסיפא, Ika de-matni lah mi-seifa, רבי עקיבא אומר
אינו אלא כמשיב אבידה ופטור. Rabbi Akiva omer eino ella ke-meshiv aveidah
u-patur. When Jenna says three she's returning a lost object, she's exempt.
טעמא דאמר שלוש... Ta'ama de-amar shalosh... three, she says three. הא שתים
ha shtayim presumably רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva would say if she would
say two חייב. chayav. Now that's aggressive, that's the reverse of what
we said before. It sounds like רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva because she
said three she's פטור. patur It sounds like had she said two,
she'd be חייב. chayav. Now why? והשתא דקמודי בה כהילך דמי. vehashta
dekamodi ba keileich dami.
But if she's saying two she's and the שטר says two, it's
like she's handing me the money. And nevertheless, it sounds like he
would have to make a שבועה the opposite of what we said
before. שמע מינה הילך חייב. shma mina heileich chayav. You see הילך
is חייב. chayav No. לעולם אימא לך שתים נמי פטור. l'olam eima
lach shtayim nami patur. Really
of two is פטור patur? because of all the reasons we said
before. So why does רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva say three is פטור?
patur והא דקתני שלוש veha dikatani shalosh the reason he says three
is פטור patur, is לאפוקי מדרבי שמעון בן אלעזר lafokei mi d'Rabbi
Shimon Ben Elazar דאמר מודה במקצת הטענה הוי d'amar modeh miketzat hata'ana
hovei because that's the easiest way to read the משנה. Everybody agrees
two is פטור, patur that's off the table. Once you say three
רבי שמעון בן אלעזר Rabbi Shimon Ben Elazar says that's a מודה
במקצת and רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says it's a משיב אבידה meishiv
aveida וחייב קא משמע לן דמשיב אבידה הוא פטור. ve'chayav kamashma lan
de'meishiv aveida hu patur. Okay, הכי נמי מסתברא. hachi nami mistavra. The
גמרא says you know what that makes sense to say that everybody
agrees two you're פטור patur, and they're debating
three. דאי סלקא דעתך שתים חייב dee salka daitach shtayim chayav if
you were to think two you'd be חייב chayav בשלוש היכי פטר
ליה רבי עקיבא? beshalosh heichi patar lei Rabbi Akiva? Then how could
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva say two you're חייב chayav. three you're פטור,
patur. you're a משיב אבידה? meishiv aveida? Okay, anybody who has a
little brains would know here's a great way to get out of
making a שבועה. הא ערומי קא מערים. ha arumei qamaraim. The person
could just be deceitful. סבר אימא שתים ובעינא אשתבועי. svar eima shtayim
ve'ba'inei ishtavu'ei. If I were to say two, I'd have to take
a שבועה. אימא שלוש דהוה כמשיב אבידה. eima shalosh de'havei k'meishiv aveida.
This is already exploiting, you know, these ideas. If משיב אבידה meishiv
aveida is a way to be nice to you to get you
off from making a שבועה because you did a good deed, so
you could actually be lying but say I'll do it in this
way. Real debt of a thousand. I could have said minimally I
could have said two. And but if I would have said two
I'd have to take a שבועה. So I'll say three. Alright, so
fine, I'll say three instead of a thousand. So obviously the fact
is so therefore okay
פטור. patur. So wait a minute, הוה כמשיב אבידה ואיפטר. havei k'meishiv
aveida ve'iftar. אלא שמע מינה שתים נמי פטור. ela shma mina shtayim
nami patur. Right. Clearly that's פשט pshat in the ברייתא braita what
we said before. Two you're פטור. patur. Okay, because it's הילך, it's
עדים, it's קרקעות. karkaos. Two you're פטור. patur. Three רבי ישמעאל Rabbi
Yishmael says that turns it into
a רבי who is it? Rabbi whatever בן אלעזר רבי שמעון בן
אלעזר Rabbi Shimon Ben Elazar says that turns it into a מודה
במקצת and רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says that's a משיב אבידה. meishiv
aveida. But two you're פטור. patur Either because הילך you're פטור patur
or because witnesses back up the claim or because of קרקע. karkao.
Okay yes? You still pay the two. You're פטור patur on a
שבועה. Okay and let's read one more line. אי נמי inami okay
גמרא says שמע מינה שתים פטור. shma mina shtayim patur. ואלא ve'ela
back so this is just a repeat of what we said before.
אלא קשיא לרבי חייא ela kashya le'Rabbi Chiya that says that two
is that הילך is חייב. So it says it's not about הילך
why you're פטור patur by two. The reason you're פטור patur. in
a שבועה by two is שאני התם דקמסייע ליה שטר shani hatam
deka mesayayei shtar because the שטר backs up the claim and that's
why you're פטור. אי נמי inami משום דהוה ליה שטר שעבוד קרקעות
mishum de'havei lei shtar shibud karkaos or because if you're only admitting
to two, your admission only consists of the liens and אין נשבעין
על כפירת שעבוד קרקעות ein nishba'in al kfirat shibud karkaos and you're
not making a שבועה on denying liens of land or the חידוש
chidush here is or even on admitting liens of land. If your
admission is only about liens or your denial is only about liens
there's not going to be any type of a שבועה. Okay so
we will pick up with this tomorrow.